All right, team,
stay in sight of each other.
Let's make NASA proud today.
How's it looking
over there, Watney?
Well,
you'll be happy to hear...
that in Grid Section 14-28,
the particles were
predominantly coarse...
but in 29,
they're much finer...
and they should be ideal
for chem analysis.
Oh, wow.
Did everybody hear that?
Mark just discovered dirt.
Should we
alert the media?
Sorry, what are you
doing today, Martinez?
Making sure the MAV
is still upright?
I'd like you to know
that visual inspection
of the equipment...
is imperative
to mission success.
I also would like to report
that the MAV is still upright.
Watney,
you keep leaving
your channel open...
which leads to
Martinez responding...
all of us listening...
which leads to me
being annoyed.
Roger that.
Martinez, the captain
would like you to please...
shut your smart mouth.
We'd prefer to use
a different adjective
to describe Martinez's mouth.
Did Beck
just insult me?
"Dr. Beck. " And yes.
Happy to turn the radios off
from here, Commander.
Just say the word.
Wait, Johanssen.
Constant communication
is the hallmark...
Shut 'em off.
No.
No. Excuse me.
I apologize
for my countrymen, Vogel.
Accepted.
How many samples
do we need, Commander?
Seven.
100 grams each.
We have a mission update.
A storm warning.
Commander,
you should come inside.
You're gonna want to see this.
What is it?
A storm warning.
I saw that
in this morning's briefing.
We'll be inside
before it hits.
Yeah, they upgraded
their estimate.
The storm's gonna be
a lot worse.
Martinez,
how does it look?
Not good.
"1,200 kilometers in diameter,
bearing 24.41 degrees."
That's tracking
right towards us.
"Based on current escalation,
"estimated force
of 8,600 newtons."
What's the abort force?
7,500.
Anything more than
that and the MAV could tip.
Do we scrub?
Begin abort procedure.
We are estimating
with a margin of error.
We could wait it out.
Let's wait it out.
Commander?
Prep emergency departure.
We're scrubbed.
That's an order.
Martinez,
how long before take-off?
12 minutes.
Visibility
is almost zero.
Anyone gets lost,
hone in on
my suit's telemetry.
You ready?
Ready.
Commander,
are you okay?
I'm okay.
Commander,
we're at 10 degrees,
and the MAV
is gonna tip at 12.3.
Hey! We might be able
to keep the MAV from tipping.
How?
Use the cables from the comms
mast as guy-lines...
anchor it with the Rover's.
Watch out!
Watney!
Warning. Suit breach detected.
What happened?
He was hit.
Watney, report.
Before we lost telemetry,
his decompression alarm
went off.
Where did you
last see him?
I don't know where he is.
What are the vitals
on his suit?
He's offline.
A complete loss
of signal on Watney.
Beck!
Yeah.
How long can he survive
decompression?
Less than a minute.
Line up, walk west.
He may be prone.
We don't wanna step over him.
Commander...
We're at 10.5 degrees.
Warning. Excessive tilt.
Tilting to 11
with all the gusts of wind.
Copy that.
Everyone, hone in
on Martinez's suit.
It'll get you to airlock.
Get in, prep for launch.
What about you,
Commander?
I'm gonna search
a little longer. Get moving!
Go!
Watney!
Watney, report!
The MAV's
at 11.6 degrees.
One good gust
and we're tipping.
If it tips, you launch.
You really think
I'm gonna leave you behind?
That's an order,
Martinez.
Mark!
Mark! Can you hear me?
Martinez, what about
the proximity radar?
Could that detect
Watney's suit?
It's made to see
the Hermes from orbit...
not a little piece of metal
from a single suit.
Give it a try.
Roger.
What is she thinking?
She knows
the infrared can't
get through a sandstorm.
She's grasping
for anything.
We've got
negative contact
on the proximity radar.
Nothing?
No.
I can barely see the Hab.
Commander, I know you don't
wanna hear this, but...
Mark is dead.
Commander!
Hey, what the hell
is wrong with you, man?
My friend just died.
I don't want
my commander to die, too.
Stability warning.
We're tipping!
Commander, you need
to get back to the ship, now!
13 degrees.
If we pass balance,
we'll never rock back.
I've got
one more trick left,
and then I'm following orders,
Commander.
You're firing the OMS?
That's right.
Commander!
On my way.
Johanssen, let's go.
Mark!
We're at 11.5
and holding.
Ready to go on your command.
Ready to launch.
Commander.
I need you to verbally tell me
whether or not to.
Launch.
Subtitle | www.movieddl.me
At around 4:30 a.m.
Central Standard Time...
our satellites
detected a storm
approaching the Ares 3
mission site on Mars.
At 6:45, the storm
had escalated to severe...
and we had no choice
but to abort the mission.
Thanks to the quick action
of Commander Lewis...
astronauts Beck, Johanssen,
Martinez and Vogel...
were all able to reach
the Mars Ascent Vehicle...
and perform an emergency
launch at 7:28 Central Time.
Unfortunately,
during the evacuation...
astronaut Mark Watney was
struck by debris and killed.
Commander Lewis
and the rest of her team...
were able to intercept safely
with the Hermes
and are now heading home.
But Mark Watney is dead.
Director Sanders!
Oxygen level critical.
Oxygen level...
Pressure stable.
Fuck.
Okay.
Hello, this is Mark Watney,
astronaut.
I'm entering this log
for the record...
in case I don't make it.
It is 06:53 on Sol 19...
and I'm alive.
Obviously.
But I'm guessing that's gonna
come as a surprise
to my crew mates and to NASA.
And to the entire world,
really, so...
Surprise.
I did not die on Sol 18.
Best I can figure...
this length of our primary
communications antenna
broke off...
and tore through
my bio-monitor...
and ripped a hole
in me as well.
But the antenna
and the blood, really,
managed to seal the breach
in my suit...
which kept me alive,
even though the crew
must have thought I was dead.
I have no way to contact NASA.
And even if I could,
it's gonna be four years...
until a manned mission
can reach me.
And I'm in a Hab designed
to last 31 days.
If the oxygen at or breaks,
I'm gonna suffocate.
If the water reclaimer breaks,
I'll die of thirst.
If the Hab breaches,
I'm just gonna, kind of...
implode.
And if by some miracle,
none of that happens...
eventually I'm gonna
run out of food.
So...
yeah.
Yeah.
I'm not gonna die here.
32...
33...
34...
35, 36.
Sweet and sour chicken.
What do we got?
Solanum tuberosum.
Right, let's do the math.
Our surface mission here was
supposed to last 31 sols.
For redundancy, they sent
68 sols worth of food.
That's for 6 people.
So for just me,
that's gonna last 300 sols...
which I figure I can stretch
to 400 if I ration.
So I got to figure out
a way to grow
three years' worth
of food here.
On a planet
where nothing grows.
Luckily...
I'm a botanist.
Mars will come to fear
my botany powers.
Pressure stable.
Staple came out.
Fuck you, Mars.
Johanssen, Jesus.
Sunday, Monday, Happy Days
Tuesday,
Wednesday, Happy Days
Thursday, Friday, Happy Days
The weekend comes,
my cycle hums
Ready to race to you
The problem is water.
I have created
126 square meters of soil.
But every cubic meter
of soil requires
40 liters of water
to be farm able.
So I gotta make
a lot more water.
Good thing is,
I know the recipe.
You take hydrogen,
you add oxygen, you burn.
Now, I have hundreds of liters
of unused hydrazine
at the MDV.
If I run the hydrazine
over an iridium catalyst,
it'll separate into N2 and H2.
And then if I just direct the
hydrogen into a small area...
and burn it.
Luckily,
in the history of humanity...
nothing bad has ever happened
from lighting hydrogen
on fire.
NASA hates fire.
Because of the whole
"fire makes everybody die
in space" thing.
So, everything
they sent us up here with
is flame-retardant...
with the notable
exception of...
Martinez's personal items.
I am sorry, Martinez.
But if you didn't want me to
go through your stuff...
you shouldn't have left me
for dead on a desolate planet.
By the way, I'm figuring
you're gonna be
fine with this,
given my present situation.
What's everybody doing?
Taking a holiday
from being cool?
Counting on you.
Whoo!
So, yeah, I blew myself up.
Best guess...
I forgot to account
for the excess oxygen...
that I've been exhaling
when I did my calculations.
Because I'm stupid.
Yeah, I'm gonna
get back to work here...
just as soon as my ears
stop ringing.
Interesting side note,
this is actually how the Jet
Propulsion Lab was founded.
Five guys at Caltech were
trying to make rocket fuel...
and they nearly burned down
their dorm.
And rather than expel them...
they banished them
to a nearby farm,
told them to keep working.
And now we have
a space program.
Okay.
Hey, there.
The nation
was blessed
to have Mark serving
in our space program.
While his loss
will be deeply felt...
the men and women of NASA
will soldier forth...
onward and upward in the
mission of their agency.
By doing so,
they honor the legacy
Mark's leaving behind...
and they ensure his sacrifice
will not be in vain.
I have the honor of speaking
not only for the men
and women of NASA...
but for people
all over the world...
I thought you gave
a lovely speech, by the way.
I need you to authorize
my satellite time.
It's not gonna happen.
We're funded
for five Ares missions.
I think I can get Congress
to authorize a sixth.
No.
Ares 3 evac'd
after 18 sols.
There's half a mission
worth of supplies up there.
I can sell it
at a fraction
of the cost of
a normal mission...
and all I have to know is
what's left of our assets.
You're not the only one
who needs satellite time.
We've got the Ares 4 supply
missions coming up.
We should be focusing on
the Schiaparelli Crater.
Okay, we got
12 satellites up there.
Surely we can spare
a few hours...
It's not about
the satellite time, Vince.
We're a public domain
organization.
We need to be
transparent on this.
Okay.
The second we point
the satellites at the Hab...
I broadcast pictures
of Mark Watney's dead body
to the world.
You're afraid of a PR problem?
Of course
I'm afraid of a PR problem.
Another mission?
Congress won't reimburse us
for a paper clip...
if I put a dead astronaut
on the front page
of The Washington Post.
He's not going anywhere,
Teddy. I mean, he's not...
He's not gonna
decompose, you know.
He's gonna be
up there forever.
Meteorology estimates that
he'll be covered in sand...
from normal weather activity
within a year.
We can't wait a year.
We got work to do.
Ares 5 won't even launch
for five years.
We have plenty of time.
Okay.
Okay, consider this.
Right now,
the world's on our side.
Sympathy
for the Watney family.
Ares 6 could
bring his body home.
Now, we don't say that's
the purpose of the mission...
but we make it clear that
that would be a part of it.
We frame it that way.
More support from Congress.
But not if we wait a year.
We wait a year,
nobody gives a shit.
Vincent Kapoor?
6-2.
7-6-2.
Acidalia Planitia.
What?
Hi. Security?
This is Mindy Park in SatCon.
I need the emergency contact
for Vincent Kapoor.
Yes, him.
Yes, it's an emergency!
How sure?
100%.
You've got to be shitting me.
Prove it to me.
For a start...
the solar panels
have been cleaned.
They could have been
cleaned by wind.
Back it up. Look at Rover 2.
According to the logs,
Commander Lewis
took it out on Sol 17...
plugged it into the Hab
to recharge.
It's been moved.
She could have forgotten
to log the move.
No, not likely.
Why don't
we just ask Lewis?
Let's get on CAPCOM and
ask her directly right now.
No. No.
If Watney is really alive,
we don't want
the Ares 3 crew to know.
How can you not tell them?
They have another 10 months
on their trip home.
Space travel is dangerous.
They need to be
alert and undistracted.
But they already think
he's dead.
And they'd be devastated
to find out
they left him there alive.
I'm sorry, but you have
not thought this through.
What are we gonna say?
"Dear America...
"remember that astronaut
we killed
"and had a really
nice funeral for?
"Turns out he's alive and we
left him on Mars. Our bad.
"Sincerely, NASA."
Do you realize the shitstorm
that is about to hit us?
How are we going
to handle the public?
Legally, we have 24 hours
to release these pictures.
We release
a statement with them.
We don't want people
working it out on their own.
Yes, sir.
But if my math is right,
he's going to starve to death
long before we can help him.
Can you imagine what
he's going through up there?
He's 50 million miles
away from home.
He thinks he's totally alone.
He thinks we gave up on him.
What does that do to a man,
psychologically?
What the hell
is he thinking right now?
I'm definitely gonna
die up here...
if I have to listen to any
more god-awful disco music.
My God, Commander Lewis,
couldn't you have packed
anything from this century?
Turn the beat around
No, I am not gonna
"turn the beat around."
I refuse to.
Mr. Sanders? Mr. Sanders?
What attempts have been made
to make contact
with Mark Watney?
We're working on it.
Does he have
enough supplies to survive?
We'll be looking into that.
What does this say
about the agency?
Are you gonna resign?
No.
Director Sanders!
It's time to start
thinking long term.
The next NASA mission
is Ares 4...
and it's supposed to land
at Schiaparelli Crater...
3200 kilometers away.
3,200 kilometers.
In four years, when the next
Ares crew arrives,
I'll have to be there.
Which means
I have to get to the crater.
Okay, so here's the rub.
I've got one working Rover
designed to go a max distance
of 35 kilometers...
before the battery has to be
recharged at the Hab.
That's Problem A.
Problem B is this journey's
gonna take me
roughly 50 days to complete.
So I gotta live for 50 days...
inside a Rover
with marginal life support
the size of a small van.
So, in the face of overwhelming
odds, I'm left with only one option.
I'm gonna have to
science the shit out of this.
I almost went down.
Man.
Okay, so, success.
Uh...
I have doubled my battery life
by scavenging Rover 1.
But if I use the heater...
I will burn through half
my battery every day.
If I do not use my heater,
I will be...
slowly killed by
the laws of thermodynamics.
I would love to solve this problem
right now but unfortunately...
my balls are frozen.
I can't. I'm calling it.
I'm calling it.
Good news,
I may have a solution
to my heating problem.
Bad news,
it involves me digging up
the Radioisotope
Thermoelectric Generator.
Now, if I remember
my training correctly,
one of the lessons
was titled...
"Don't Dig Up the Big Box
of Plutonium, Mark."
I get it. RTGs are good
for spacecraft,
but if they rupture
around humans...
no more humans.
Which is why we buried it
when we arrived.
And planted that flag...
so we would never be
stupid enough
to accidentally
go near it again.
But as long as
I don't break it...
I almost just said
"Everything will be fine"
out loud.
Look, the point is,
I'm not cold anymore.
And sure,
I could choose to think
about the fact
that I'm warm...
because I have a decaying
radioactive isotope
riding right behind me...
but right now, I got bigger
problems on my hands.
I have scoured
every single data file
on Commander Lewis'
personal drive.
This is officially
the least disco song she owns.
Lookin' for some hot stuff
Baby, this evenin'
I need some hot stuff,
baby, tonight
I want some hot stuff,
baby, this evenin'
Gotta have some hot stuff
Gotta have some love tonight
Hot stuff
I need hot stuff
I want some hot stuff
Yeah.
Where is Watney going?
We believe that
he's preparing for a journey.
He's been conducting
incremental tests...
taking the Rover 2
out for longer
and longer trips each time.
To what end?
Why would he leave
the relative safety
of the Hab?
Well, we think that he plans to
travel to the Ares 4 launch site...
in order to make
contact with us,
but it would be
a dangerous gamble.
But if we could talk to him,
we would tell him
to stay put...
and to trust that we are doing
everything in our power
to bring him home alive.
Thank you very much.
You asked me how you did,
and I'm giving you my answer.
My answer is...
Uh...
Look, I'm gonna
make people forget...
there's a very strong possibility
that Mark Watney could die...
because that is what
you are paying me for.
And unfortunately,
I need this job...
because currently I am paying
alimony to two deadbeat ex-husbands...
because somehow, gender equality
has bitten me square in the ass.
Hard to believe.
I left them.
And don't say
"Bring him home alive."
It reminds the world
he might die.
Don't say "Bring him
home alive," Vincent.
You know what? These
interviews aren't easy.
So God forbid I try to say
something proactive and positive.
Annie.
No more Vincent
on TV. Copy that.
76 kilometers.
Am I reading that right?
Are you asking me?
I am.
Yes, sir.
Mark drove two hours
straightaway from the Hab...
did a short EVA and then
drove for another two.
We think the EVA
was to change batteries.
He didn't load up
the oxygen at or
or the water reclaimer?
Every 41 hours,
there's a 17 minute gap.
It's just the way
the orbits work...
so it's possible
that we missed something.
I want that gap
down to four minutes.
I'm giving you
total authority
over satellite trajectories
and orbital adjustments.
Make it happen.
Okay.
Let's assume Miss Park
didn't miss anything.
So Mark's not going
to Ares 4. Yet.
But he's smart enough
to figure out
that's his only chance.
Bruce, what's the earliest we
can get a pre-supply there?
With the positions
of Earth and Mars,
it'll take nine months.
It'll take six months to
build it in the first place.
Three months.
Three?
You're going to say
it's impossible
and then I'm gonna
make a speech...
about the blinding
capabilities
of the JPL team...
and then you're going
to do the math
in your head
and say something like...
"The overtime alone
will be a nightmare."
The overtime alone
will be a nightmare.
Get started.
I'll find you the money.
We need to tell the crew.
Mitch,
we've discussed this.
No, you discussed this.
I'm the one who decides
what's best for the crew.
They deserve to know.
Once there's a real
rescue plan, we'll tell them.
Otherwise, it's moot.
Bruce has three months to get
the payload done.
That's all that
matters right now.
We'll do our best.
Mark dies if you don't.
It's been 48 sols
since I planted the potatoes.
So now it's time
to reap and re-sow.
They grew even better
than I expected.
I now have 400
healthy potato plants.
I dug them up, being careful
to leave their plants alive.
The smaller ones I'll reseed,
the larger ones
are my food supply.
All natural, organic,
Martian-grown potatoes.
You don't hear
that every day, do you?
And by the way,
none of this matters at all...
if I can't figure out a way
to make contact with NASA.
I know what I'm gonna do.
Oh! He's moving again.
Where the hell
is he going?
He hasn't changed course
for 13 days.
He's nowhere near the Ares 4.
Unless he's not taking
a direct route.
He might be trying to avoid
some obstacle.
What obstacle?
It's Acidalia Planitia.
There's nothing out there
except the...
What?
I need a map.
Yeah.
Hey, come on.
What are you doing?
It's all right.
Can I borrow this?
Okay, so where
is the Hab location?
31 .2 degrees north,
28.5 degrees west.
Okay. Mmm-hmm.
Where's Watney?
Uh...
There.
Okay.
Okay. I know where he's going.
I need to get on an airplane.
Vincent, how are you?
Good to see you.
Good flight?
Uh...
Yeah.
It's in storage
just around the corner.
Hey, Vincent,
nice to see you again.
Nice to see you.
What are the chances Mark
can get it working again?
It's hard to say.
We lost contact in '97.
We think
it was battery failure.
Though I'd like to point out
it lasted three times longer
than expected in any...
Nobody's criticizing
JPL's work, Bruce.
I just need to speak
to everybody
that was here in '97.
They're already
here. Guys.
I'd like to introduce
Vincent Kapoor.
Director of Mars Missions
for NASA.
This is our current team...
and our original
project members.
- Is this the replica?
- This is her.
Okay. Let's see it.
Pathfinder.
Come on. Come on.
Holy shit. Okay.
"Broadcasting status.
"Listening
for telemetry signal."
Uh-huh.
Okay. Signal acquired.
- All right.
- Okay.
Camera.
Okay, taking
panoramic image now.
You receiving yet?
Yeah.
I just thought we'd all rather
look at a black screen...
instead of a vibrant
red planet.
Excuse me?
Tim's our finest comm tech.
We all appreciate
his acerbic wit.
I will kill you.
Incoming.
"Are you receiving me?"
"Yes. No."
Okay, point
the camera at "yes."
32-minute round-trip
communications time.
All he can do
is ask yes or no questions...
and all we can do
is point the camera.
This won't exactly be
an Algonquin Round Table
of snappy repartee.
Are you kidding me?
Tim, Tim.
- Just point the camera.
- Roger that.
Pointing the camera.
Whoo!
Yes!
So here's the rub.
Somehow we have
to have complex
astrophysical engineering
conversations...
Using nothing but
a still-frame camera...
from 1996.
Luckily...
the camera does spin.
So I can make an alphabet.
It can't be our alphabet.
26 characters plus
a question card
into 360 gives us
13 degrees of arc.
That's way too narrow.
I'd never know what the camera
was pointing at.
Ooh.
Hexadecimals.
Hexadecimals to the rescue.
I figured one of you guys
kept an ASCll table
lying around.
And I was right.
Ladies and gentlemen,
I give you super-nerd
Beth Johanssen.
Who also had copies
of Zork ll...
and Leather Goddesses of
Phobos on her personal laptop.
Seriously, Johanssen...
it's like the Smithsonian
of loneliness on there.
Not that I'm complaining.
Yes!
Who am I to talk
about loneliness?
I know where
he's going with this.
"F, O."
"7, W."
Vincent.
Vincent, wake up.
Now that we can have more
complicated conversations...
the smart people at NASA
have sent me instructions
on how to hack the Rover...
so that it can talk
to Pathfinder.
If I hack
a tiny bit of code...
just 20 instructions in the
Rover's operating system...
NASA can link
the Rover to Pathfinder's
broadcasting frequency...
and we're in business.
"Mark...
"this is Vincent Kapoor.
"We've been
watching you since Sol 54.
"The whole world
is rooting for you.
"Amazing job
getting Pathfinder.
"We're working
on rescue plans.
"Meantime, we're putting
together a supply mission...
"to keep you fed
until Ares 4 arrives."
Okay.
"Glad to hear it. Really
looking forward to not dying."
"How's the crew?"
"What did they say when they
found out I was alive?"
Guys, can we get
some space please?
Me?
Yeah, you.
Give me a sec.
Just tell him.
"We haven't told the crew
you are alive yet.
"We need them to concentrate
on their mission."
What the fuck?
Okay, he says,
"They don't know I'm alive?
"What the..." F-word.
F-word in gerund form.
F-word, again,
"is wrong with you?"
"Mark, please
watch your language.
"Everything you type
"is being broadcast live
all over the world."
Yeah?
Oh, my God.
What's a fetcher?
Yes, sir. He is under
a tremendous amount of stress.
I understand.
We're working on it.
Thank you,
Mr. President.
I just had to explain to the
President of the United States...
what a beaurocratic
fetcher is.
I made the mistake
of typing it into Google.
Don't.
Problem is,
Mark's right.
The longer we wait,
the worse it's gonna get.
We need to tell the crew.
You're bringing this up while
Vincent is in Pasadena...
so he can't argue
the other side.
I shouldn't have
to answer to Vincent.
Or anyone else.
It's time, Teddy.
Commander Lewis?
Go ahead.
Data dump
is almost complete.
Copy that. On my way.
You're in a hurry.
Yeah.
My son turned
three yesterday.
Should be pictures
of the party.
Got a batch
of personals.
Dispatching them
to your laptops now.
I don't need to read Vogel's
weird German fetish emails.
They're
telemetry updates.
Hey, whatever
does it for you, man.
There's a video message.
It's addressed
to the whole crew.
Play it. Come on, guys.
I wanna get in on
that telemetry action.
Hi, hello. It's Mitch.
Mitch Henderson.
I have some news.
There's no subtle way
to put this.
Mark Watney is still alive.
Oh, my God.
I know that's a surprise
and I know
you will have
a lot of questions.
But here are the basics.
He's alive and he's healthy.
We found out two months ago
and decided not to tell you.
Two months?
Oh, my God.
I was strongly
against that decision.
We're telling you
now because...
we finally have
communication with him...
and a viable rescue plan.
We'll give you a write-up
of what happened,
a full write-up of everything.
But it's not your fault.
Mark stresses that
every time it comes up.
So... Yeah...
Take some time to absorb this.
And send all
the questions you want.
We'll answer them.
All right. Henderson out.
Holy shit, he's alive.
I left him behind.
- No.
We all left together.
You were following orders.
I left him behind.
So now that
NASA can talk to me,
they won't shut up.
They want constant updates
on every Hab system...
and they got
a room full of people
trying to micromanage
my crops.
Which is awesome.
Look, I don't mean to sound
arrogant or anything...
but I am the greatest botanist
on this planet, so...
One big bonus
to this communication
with NASA again...
is the email.
I'm getting them again.
Big data dumps
like when I was on the Hermes.
I even got one
from the president.
The coolest one, though,
the coolest one I got...
was from
University of Chicago,
my Alma mater.
They say that once you
grow crops somewhere...
you've officially
colonized it.
So, technically...
I colonized Mars.
In your face, Neil Armstrong.
In other news,
there's been a request...
for me to pose
for a photograph
on my next transmission.
I'm trying
to figure out whether
I should go with
"High School Senior"...
or "coquettish ingénue."
But I'm not really sure
how that's gonna look
with my spacesuit on.
Hey!
What is he doing?
I asked for a photo, and what,
he's The Fonz?
Just be grateful
we got you something, Annie.
I can't use this, Vincent,
and you know that.
I need a picture of his face.
I could tell him
to take off his helmet...
but then he'd, you know,
die, so...
We'll release
the photo
when we detail
the rescue operation.
I want to announce
we're launching
some supplies to him
next year...
during the Hohmann
Transfer Window.
Bruce, your team's still
on schedule?
It'll be tight,
but we'll make it.
Nine-month travel time.
That puts the probe
to Mars on Sol 868.
Did we get
the botany team's analysis?
Yeah, they estimate Mark's
crops will last till Sol 912.
They grudgingly admit that
he's doing great work.
Grudgingly?
Yeah. Mark has a tendency
to tell them
to have sex with themselves...
whenever they question
one of his decisions.
Get him
in line, Vincent.
We can't afford
any miscommunication.
I hate this margin.
912 Sols worth of food.
We get there on 868.
And that's assuming
nothing goes wrong.
Suit breach detected.
Oxygen level critical.
Oxygen level, 10%.
Oxygen level, 5%.
Suit pressure, stable.
Pressure stable.
God! God, God, God, God!
Crops are dead.
Complete loss of pressure
boiled off most of the water.
Any bacteria that survived,
died in the subzero
temperatures...
when exposed to
Mars' atmosphere.
How long does he have?
He can still eat
the potatoes he has,
he just can't grow any more...
so give him 200 sols.
Rations get him to what?
Sol 409?
Mmm-hmm.
So with potatoes, 609.
So by Sol 868,
he'll be long dead.
We're gonna have to launch
as soon as possible...
which changes our travel time.
Yeah, we're working on it.
Prelim estimates call
for a 414-day trip.
It's Sol 135 now.
We need 13 days
to mount the boosters,
perform inspections...
which gives
Bruce and his team...
47 days to make this probe.
I'll let you call Bruce,
give him the news.
Okay.
I'm gonna need
a change of clothes.
"Dear Mark...
"Apparently NASA's letting us
talk to you now.
"And I drew the short straw.
"Sorry we left you
behind on Mars.
"But we just don't like you.
"Also, it's a lot roomier
on the Hermes without you.
"We have to take turns
doing your tasks.
"But, I mean,
it's only botany.
"It's not real science."
Oh, Jesus.
"How's Mars?"
"Dear Martinez,
Mars is fine.
"I accidentally
blew up the Hab...
"but unfortunately,
"all of Commander Lewis'
disco music still survived."
"But unfortunately,
"all of Commander Lewis'
disco music still survived."
"Every day,
I go outside
"and look at
the vast horizons."
"Every day,
I go outside
"and look at
the vast horizons."
"Just because I can."
"Just because I can.
"Tell the others
I said hello."
"Will do, buddy."
Pressure stable.
5, 10...
15, 20, 30, 35...
40.
52.
Rich.
Wake up.
Sorry, but they're asking for
the probe courses.
What time is it?
It's 3:42.
Look, I know we're
coming at this backwards...
but we can't commit
to a firm launch date
with this many unknowns.
It's all right. Um...
All 25 models for launch will
take 414 days to reach Mars.
They vary slightly
in thrust duration...
and the fuel requirement
is nearly identical.
Not a good time
to launch, is it?
Yeah, Earth and Mars
are really badly positioned.
Heck, it'd almost
be easier if you...
Almost easier to what?
I need more coffee.
Ahh!
Are you all right?
It's fine.
Almost easier to what?
You do understand
I'm your boss, right?
Uh-huh.
Okay, let's ask
the $200 million...
I'm sorry 500...
Is that a 5?
At least.
All right, let's ask
the very, very expensive question.
Is the probe going
to be ready on time?
We're behind.
Give me a number.
15 days. 15 days
and I can get it done.
All right, let's
create 15 days.
13 days to mount the probe.
Can we reduce?
It actually only takes three
days to mount the probe.
And we can get that down
to two, right?
I can get it down to two.
10 days are for tests
and inspections.
How often do those inspections
reveal a problem?
Are you suggesting
we don't do the inspections?
Right now I'm asking how often
they reveal a problem.
One in 20.
But that's grounds
for countdown halt.
We can't take
that chance.
Anyone else know a safer way
to buy more time?
Dr. Keller, stretch Watney's
rations four more days.
You're not gonna like it,
but that'll get us to 15.
And we'll cancel
the inspections.
Teddy.
Sir, if that ever got out...
It's on me.
You got your two weeks.
Get it done.
So,
now I have to hold out
until the probe gets here
with more food.
You want to see what minimal
calorie count looks like?
Standard issue ration.
But instead of three of
these every one day...
I'm now eating one of these
every three days.
This is meatloaf.
So, here's today's
allotment...
which, of course, I've
supplemented with a potato...
which I'm beginning to hate
with the fiery passion...
of 1,000 suns.
And now, they've asked me...
to do that.
The point is...
"stretch the rations
four more days"...
is a real dick-punch.
I'm gonna dip this potato
in some crushed Vicodin.
And there's nobody
who can stop me.
It has been seven days
since I ran out of ketchup.
And since we've
pushed launch...
we need to account for the
new satellite adjustments.
We still haven't received
the old satellite adjustments.
Well, I asked for those
two weeks ago.
What's Rich doing?
We're scared to go in there.
Rich, what the hell
are you doing?
I need you to get me
some supercomputer time.
When did you last sleep?
It's important, Mike.
All right,
I'll do it.
Good.
Up. Up, up. Yeah.
Let's go up here.
Labels facing up.
This is the flight director.
Begin launch status check.
Roger that, Flight.
Beginning launch status check.
Do you believe
in God, Vincent?
Yeah.
Yeah, my father
was a Hindu,
my mother's a Baptist,
so, yeah...
I believe in several.
We'll take all
the help we can get.
Launch status check complete.
This is Flight.
We are go for launch.
Proceeding with the count.
10... 9...
8...
7... 6...
Main engines start.
4... 3...
2...
1.
Liftoff.
Good thrust.
Performance is nominal.
The tail is giving good data.
She's rock
solid at this point, Flight.
TVCs look good.
We're getting
a little shimmy, Flight.
Say again?
We are getting
a very large precession.
Are we good?
Flight,
it's hitting the red line.
It's spinning on the long axis
around a 17-degree precession.
Launch, what's happening?
Force on Iris is 7 G's.
We've lost
readings on the probe, Flight.
Oh, Jesus Christ.
We've lost it, Flight.
SatCon?
No satellite acquisition
of signal.
L.O.S.
L.O.S. here, too.
U.S. Destroyer Stockton
reporting debris
falling from the sky.
Everyone in the ICC,
maintain your positions
at your consoles.
GC, lock the doors.
"Commander Lewis...
"I may need you
to do something for me.
"If I die, I need you to
check in on my parents.
"They'll wanna hear all about
our time here on Mars.
"I know that sucks.
"And it'll be hard
talking to a couple...
"about their dead son.
"It's a lot to ask.
"Which is why I'm asking you.
"I'm not giving up.
"We just need to prepare
for every outcome.
"Please tell them...
"Tell them I love what I do...
"and I'm really good at it.
"And that I'm dying...
"for something big...
"and beautiful...
"and greater than me.
"Tell them
I said I can live with that.
"And tell them...
"thank you for being
my mom and dad."
We substituted
protein cubes
for the standard rations.
The thrust
of the launch combined
with the simultaneous
lateral vibration...
liquefied the cubes and
created an unbalanced load.
Vincent, why wasn't
this addressed
in the inspections phase?
In order to make
our launch window,
we were forced
to accelerate our schedule.
Their astronaut
is going to die.
Of course there
are other ways...
...the Tat yang Shen booster. Our
engineers have run the numbers,
and it has enough fuel
for a Mars injection orbit.
Why hasn't NASA
approached us?
They don't know.
Our booster technology
is classified.
So if we do nothing...
The world would never know
we could have helped.
Then, for the sake of argument,
let's say we decide to help them...
We'd be giving up a booster and
effectively cancelling Tat yang Shen.
We need to keep this among scientists,
a co-operation between space agencies.
Yes.
Yes, I understand.
Thank you.
Yes!
All right.
Thanks to my uncle Tommy
in China,
we get another chance at this.
Now, we finished
the Iris probe in 62 days.
We are now gonna attempt
to finish it in 28.
We can jettison
any kind of landing system.
We're only sending rations.
We can crash-land on Mars.
You should hang up
the phone.
I'm sorry, who are you?
My name is Rich Purnell.
I work in Astrodynamics,
and you should hang up
the phone right now.
All right, all right.
I'm gonna call you back.
I know how to
save Mark Watney.
Your probe plan won't work.
Too many things can go wrong.
I've got a better way.
Astrodynamics?
Yeah.
What the hell
is "Project Elrond"?
I had to
make something up.
But "Elrond"?
Because it's a secret meeting.
How do you know that?
Why does "Elrond" mean
"secret meeting"?
The Council of Elrond.
It's from Lord of the Rings.
Lord of the Rings.
It's the meeting where they
decide to destroy the One Ring.
if we're gonna call
something "Project Elrond"...
I would like my code name
to be "Glorfindel."
Okay, I hate
every one of you.
What, Teddy doesn't even
know about this yet?
I'm sorry,
who are you?
This is Rich Purnell,
Astrodynamics.
Tell them what
you just told me.
I can get the Hermes
back to Mars by Sol 561.
How?
Could you stand right
there for me, please?
Thanks.
Right there. Great.
And could you stand
right there? Right there.
Okay, let's pretend that
this stapler is the Hermes...
and you are...
I'm sorry,
what's your name again?
Teddy. I'm the Director
of NASA.
Cool. Teddy,
you're Earth.
And right now, the Hermes
is headed towards you...
starting its month-long
deceleration to intercept.
But instead,
what I'm proposing is...
We start accelerating
immediately
to preserve velocity
and gain even more.
We don't intercept
with Earth at all...
but we come close enough
to get a gravity assist
and adjust course.
While we're doing that...
we resupply with the probe...
The Tat yang Shen.
...pick up whatever
provisions we need...
and now we're accelerating
towards Mars.
You're Mars.
Now, we're going too fast
at this point to fall into orbit...
but we can do a flyby.
What good is a flyby if we
can't get Watney off the surface?
Watney would intercept
using the MAV.
Ow!
And then we just head home.
I've done the math.
It checks out.
Rich.
Yes, sir.
Get out.
All right.
- Is he right?
- Yeah.
Bruce,
what do you think?
Well, if Vincent says so.
We need to use
the Tat yang Shen?
Uh-huh.
What am I missing?
Why is that important?
Because we can only do one.
Send Watney enough food
to last till Ares 4...
or send Hermes back
to get him right now.
Both plans require
the Tat yang Shen,
so we have to choose.
But what about
the Hermes crew?
We'd be asking them to add
533 extra days
to their mission.
Yeah. They wouldn't hesitate,
not for a second.
Can the Hermes function for 533
days beyond the scheduled mission end?
It should.
Built to last
the full Ares mission...
so technically, it's only
halfway through its lifespan.
But if something goes wrong...
Then we lose the crew.
So what?
We either have a high chance
of killing one person...
or a low chance
of killing six people.
How do we make
that decision?
We don't have to
make it, Bruce.
He does.
Yeah, well, bullshit.
It should be
Commander Lewis' call.
We still have a chance to bring
five astronauts home safe and sound.
I'm not risking
their lives.
Let them make
that decision.
Mitch, we're going
with option one.
You goddamn coward.
So, he's been doing
EVAs throughout the day?
But there's a pattern to
them. Here, watch this.
So, he goes 300 meters
and then stops.
Then he goes another
300 and stops.
Nobody's giving him
any instructions?
JPL didn't schedule
something?
No. He's with the Rover.
Okay, so we just got this.
Chem analysis sample
batch 1A7C.
Commander Lewis'
fuel compositing experiments.
He's finishing the mission.
Wow.
We evac'd 18 sols
into a 31 -sol mission.
Which means...
we've got 13 sols' worth of
experiment and research left to do.
So, Commander Lewis...
your work is in good hands.
Hey, Beck...
I do not understand
chemolithotrophic detection.
I mean, at all.
But I'm working on it,
working my way through it.
Hey, Johanssen...
I know you don't like it
when I touch the ChemCam.
But...
I'm touching the ChemCam.
A lot.
Vogel, your core samples...
in very good hands.
Actually...
I think I found
a new cataloguing system...
for the core samples.
I've actually titled it
"Das Core Samples"
out of respect
for the fatherland.
And finally, Martinez...
I'm still not sure
what it is that you do.
Honest to God,
I really couldn't tell you.
I don't know
why we brought you.
That's it.
Anyway, I'm trying to keep
everything documented, organized.
I know it's not
my strong suit...
but I do want everything
to make sense.
Just in case things
don't break my way.
Actually, you could teach
all this in a class someday.
You know, the good stuff,
like how to make a bathtub...
using NASA tubing
and an old RTG.
How to cook a potato
about 6,000 different ways.
The Mark Watney syllabus.
Johanssen?
Yeah.
I know it's your private time.
Can I bother you for a second?
Yeah, go ahead.
Where are you?
The gym.
What's up?
I just got an email
from my wife
and the subject line
says, "Our children."
My computer won't open
the attachment.
Okay.
Let's take a look.
Uh...
Let's see.
This isn't a JPEG.
It's a plain ASCll text file.
I don't really know
what we're looking at.
Does that make
any sense to you?
"Rich Purnell Maneuver."
It's a course maneuver
for the Hermes.
And the mission concludes
with Earth intercept,
211 days later.
Would it work?
Mmm-hmm. We ran
the numbers. They check out.
It's a
brilliant course.
So why all
the cloak and dagger?
Because it goes directly
against NASA's decision.
Yeah. If we do
the maneuver,
they'd have to send
the supply ship or we die.
We have the opportunity
to force their hand.
So, are we gonna do it?
If it was up to me,
we'd already be on our way.
But it is, though,
isn't it? Up to you.
Not this time.
This is something NASA
expressly rejected.
We're talking about
mutiny here,
which is not a word
that I take lightly.
So we do this together
or not at all.
And before you answer,
consider the consequences.
If we mess up the supply
rendezvous, we die.
If we mess up the Earth
gravity assist, we die.
If we do everything
perfectly...
we add 533 days
to our mission.
533 more days before
we see our families again.
533 days of unplanned
space travel...
where anything could go wrong.
If it's mission
critical, we die.
Sign me up.
All right, cowboy,
slow down.
You and I, we're military.
Chances are, we go home,
they'll court martial us.
Yeah, there's that.
And for the rest
of you guys...
I guarantee they will never
send you back up here again.
Good. So, if we go
for it, how would it work?
I plot the course
and execute it.
Remote override.
They could take
over the Hermes
from Mission Control.
Can you disable it?
Hermes has four redundant
flight computers...
each connected to three
redundant comm systems.
We can't shut down
the comms
because we'd lose
telemetry and guidance.
And we can't shut down
the computers
because we need
to run the ship.
I'd have to disable remote
override on each system.
It's part of the OS, I'd have
to jump over the code.
Okay, but, like, in English,
what would that mean?
I can do it.
Great.
Well, it has
to be unanimous.
If we do this, it'll be
over 900 days of space.
That's more than enough
space for one life...
so, yes.
I vote yes.
Let's go get him.
Johanssen?
Yes.
Yeah!
But how are you
gonna do that?
Got an unscheduled status
update from Hermes.
Roger. Read it out.
Message reads,
"Houston, please be advised.
"Rich Purnell
is a steely-eyed missile man."
What?
Flight, Guidance.
Hermes is off-course.
CAPCOM, advise Hermes
they're drifting.
Guidance, get
a correction ready.
Negative, Flight,
it's not drift.
They've adjusted course.
What the hell?
Telemetry, any chance this is
instrumentation failure?
Negative, Flight.
Guidance, work at
how long they can stay
on this course
before it's irreversible.
Working
on that now, Flight.
Hey.
Who's Rich Purnell?
I dunno.
Will somebody find out
who the hell Rich Purnell is?
Annie will go before
the media this morning...
and inform them
of NASA's decision
to reroute
the Hermes to Mars.
Sounds like a smart move.
Considering the circumstances.
Whoever gave them the maneuver
only passed along information.
Crew made the decision
on their own.
You may have
killed them, Mitch.
We're fighting the same war.
Every time
something goes wrong,
the world forgets why we fly.
I'm trying
to keep us airborne.
It's bigger than one person.
No.
It's not.
When this is over,
I'll expect your resignation.
I understand.
Bring our astronauts home.
Every Ares mission requires
three years of pre-supplies.
So NASA decided a long time
ago it's a lot easier...
to send some
of the stuff beforehand
rather than bring it with us.
So, as a result,
the MAV for Ares 4...
is already there
at the Schiaparelli Crater,
just waiting.
So the plan is for me to use
that to go into orbit...
just as the Hermes
is passing...
and I guess they catch me?
In space.
So, I've got 200 sols
to figure out...
how to take everything here
that's keeping me alive...
the oxygen at or,
the water reclaimer,
the atmospheric regulator...
bring that all with me.
And luckily,
I have the greatest minds
on Planet Earth...
really, all of the brainpower
on the entire planet...
helping me with this endeavor.
And so far
they've come up with...
"Hey, why don't you
drill holes
"on the roof of your Rover...
"and hit it as hard as you can
with a rock?"
We're gonna get there.
Didn't know
what time it was
And the lights were low
I leaned back on my radio
Some cat was la yin' down
some rock 'n' roll
Lotta soul, he said
Then the loud sound
did seem to fade
Came back like a slow voice
on a wave of phase
That weren't no DJ
That was hazy cosmic jive
There's a star man
waiting in the sky
533 days longer?
And you said yes to this?
He would have done the same
for me. You know that.
Cheese. You do "cheese"?
Cheese.
He didn't do "cheese."
Did he do "cheese"?
Hey, baby.
Hey.
I got something for you.
Found it in the flea market.
Original pressing.
No!
Not a scratch.
I love it.
All due respect
to your CNSA protocol...
but we haven't
done things that way...
since Apollo 9.
Did he get that?
Look out your window
I can see his light
If we can sparkle
He may land tonight
Mmm-hmm.
Yeah. Mmm-hmm.
Oh!
There's a star man
waiting in the sky
He'd like to
come and meet us
But he thinks
he'd blow our minds
There's a star man
waiting in the sky
He's told us not to blow it
'Cause he knows
it's all worthwhile
He told me
Let the children lose it
Let the children use it
Let all the children boogie
There's a star man
waiting in the sky
He'd like to
come and meet us
But he thinks
he'd blow our minds
There's a star man
waiting in the sky
He's told us not to blow it
'Cause he knows
it's all worthwhile
He told me
Let the children lose it
Let the children use it
Let all the children boogie
La, la, la, la,
la, la, la, la
I've been thinking
about laws on Mars.
There's an
international treaty
saying no country
can lay claim...
to anything that's
not on Earth.
And by another treaty,
if you're not in any
country's territory...
maritime law applies.
So Mars
is international waters.
Now, NASA is an American
non-military organization.
It owns the Hab.
But the second I walk outside,
I'm in international waters.
So here's the cool part.
I'm about to leave for
the Schiaparelli Crater...
where I'm gonna commandeer
the Ares 4 lander.
Nobody explicitly gave me
permission to do this...
and they can't
until I'm on board the Ares 4.
So that means I'm gonna be
taking a craft over...
in international waters
without permission.
Which, by definition,
makes me a pirate.
Mark Watney,
Space Pirate.
A Space Pirate.
Everywhere I go,
I'm the first.
It's a strange feeling.
Step outside the Rover...
first guy to be there.
Climb that hill,
first guy to do that.
Four and a half
billion years...
nobody here.
And now, me.
I'm the first person to be
alone on an entire planet.
How's he doing?
So far, so good.
He's sticking to schedule.
Drives for four hours
before noon...
lays the solar panels,
waits 13 hours for them
to recharge...
and sleeps somewhere in there
and then starts again.
How's he doing?
He asked us to call him
Captain Blondebeard.
Well, technically, Mars
would be under maritime...
Yeah, I know.
He explained it to us.
Where is he?
There.
Okay.
Here.
Okay, I'm gonna start
by stating for the record
that you're not
gonna like this.
Oh, yeah?
Yeah, the problem is
the intercept velocity.
The Hermes, well...
It can't enter Mars' orbit.
Otherwise, they'll never have
enough fuel to make it home.
The MAV, that was
only designed
to get to low Mars orbit.
So in order for Mark to
escape Mars' gravity entirely...
and to intercept
the Hermes...
He has to be
going fast. Exactly.
Which means we need to make
the MAV lighter.
A lot lighter.
5,000 kilograms lighter.
You can do that, right?
There's some gimmes
right off the bat.
The design presumes 500
kilograms of Martian soil and samples.
Obviously we won't do that.
And there's just one
passenger instead of six.
With suits and gear,
that's another 500?
Ditch the life support,
don't need it.
And we'll get Mark to wear
his EVA suit the whole trip.
Wait a second.
If he's in his EVA suit,
how is he gonna
operate the controls?
Well, he won't.
Martinez will pilot the MAV
remotely from the Hermes.
We've never had a manned ship
controlled remotely before.
But I am excited about
the opportunities
that affords.
If we go remote, we can
lose the control panels,
the secondary and tertiary
comm systems.
Wait a second.
You want a remote-controlled
ascent with no backup comms?
He's not even got to
the bad stuff yet, Vincent.
Let's skip to
the bad stuff!
We need to remove
the nose airlock,
the windows,
and Hull Panel 19.
You want to take
the front of the ship off?
Sure.
The nose airlock alone
is 400 kilograms.
You want to send a man into
space without the front of his ship?
Well, no.
We're gonna have him cover it
with Hab canvas.
Look, the hull's mostly there
to keep the air in.
Mars' atmosphere is so thin,
you don't need
a lot of streamlining.
By the time the ship's
going fast enough
for air resistance
to matter...
it'll be high enough that
there's practically no air.
You wanna send him
into space under a tarp.
Yes.
Can I go on?
No.
You think
he means it like...
"Are you kidding me?"
You know?
Mmm-hmm.
Or like,
"Are you kidding me?"
I think it might be
the second one.
Really?
Uh-huh.
Could be the first way.
"Are you kidding me?"
Yeah, it could be
the first way.
I know
what they're doing.
I know exactly
They just keep repeating...
"Go faster than any man in
the history of space travel."
Like that's a good thing.
Like it'll distract me from
how insane their plan is.
Yeah, I get to go
faster than any man
in the history
of space travel...
because you are launching me
in a convertible.
Actually it's worse than that
because I won't even be able
to control the thing.
And by the way, physicists,
when describing things
like acceleration...
do not use the word "fast."
So they're only doing that
in the hopes
that I won't raise
any objections...
to this lunacy.
Because I like the way
"fastest man in the history
of space travel" sounds.
I do like the way it sounds.
I mean, I like it a lot.
I'm not gonna tell them that.
Okay.
Let's do this.
My, my
At Waterloo
Napoleon did surrender
Oh, yeah
And I have met my destiny
in quite a similar way
The history book on the
shelf is always repeating itself
Waterloo
I was defeated
You won the war
Come on.
Waterloo, promise to
love you for evermore
Waterloo
Couldn't escape if I wanted to
Knowing my fate
is to be with you
Oh, oh, oh, oh, Waterloo
Finally facing my Waterloo
My, my
I tried to hold you back
But you were stronger
Oh, yeah
And now it seems my only
chance is giving up the fight
And how could I ever refuse?
I feel like I
win when I lose
Waterloo
I was defeated
You won the war
Waterloo
Promise to love you
for evermore
Waterloo
Couldn't escape
if I wanted to
Waterloo
Knowing my fate
is to be with you
Oh, oh, oh, oh, Waterloo
Finally facing my Waterloo
So how could I ever refuse?
I feel like I
win when I lose
Waterloo
Couldn't escape
if I wanted to
And you killed him.
Try it again.
Ooh, Waterloo
Finally facing my Waterloo
Oh, oh, oh, oh, Waterloo
How many times
you kill Watney?
The important thing is that
I got all scenarios into orbit.
That's the important thing.
- He's ready.
- Okay.
Here's the plan.
Martinez flies the MAV.
Johanssen sysops
the ascent.
Beck, Vogel, I want you guys in
Airlock 2 with the outer door open...
before the MAV
even launches. Okay.
Once we hit intercept, it's
Beck's job to go get Watney.
He may be in bad shape
when we get him.
The stripped-down MAV will get
him to 12 G's during the launch.
He could be knocked unconscious,
may even have internal bleeding.
Well, it's a good thing
you're our doctor.
What's the intercept plan?
We finished attaching the
tethers into one long line.
It's 214 meters long.
And I'll have the MMU, so
moving around should be easy.
How fast a relative velocity
can you handle?
I can grab the MAV
at 5 meters per second.
10 is like jumping
onto a moving train.
So any more than that
and I might miss.
Well, we may
have some leeway.
The launch takes 12 minutes.
And it'll be 52 minutes
before intercept.
Once Mark's
engine shuts off...
we'll know our intercept point
and velocity.
Vogel, you're Beck's backup.
Everything goes well, you pull
them on board with the tether.
If anything goes wrong,
you go out after him.
Yep.
Okay.
Let's go get our boy.
There's a mood
of tension and anxiety here,
outside Johnson Space Center.
As you can see,
many people
have gathered here...
to see whether or not
the mission to retrieve Mark
Watney will be a success.
They've had
some contact with him,
but it hasn't been very much.
We have to remind our viewers
that we're watching this
as it unfolds.
So we'll try
and keep you up-to-date
as to what exactly
is going on.
Let's listen in to NASA making
contact with Mark Watney.
Let's listen in.
If something goes wrong,
what can Mission Control do?
Not a damn thing.
It's all happening
12 light-minutes away...
which means it takes
24 minutes for them
to get the answer to any
question they ask.
The whole launch
is 12 minutes...
so they're on their own.
...just how long
Mark has been
completely alone on Mars.
We're talking to a psychology
expert later to discuss...
Fuel pressure,
green.
Engine alignment, perfect.
Communications, five by five.
We are ready for pre-flight
checklist, Commander.
Mission Control,
this is Hermes actual.
We will proceed on schedule.
We are T-minus 2 minutes,
10 seconds
to launch, by the mark.
About two minutes, Watney.
How you doing down there?
I'm good.
I'm anxious to get up to you.
Thanks for coming back for me.
Well, we're on it.
Remember, you'll be pulling
some serious G's,
so it's okay to pass out.
You're in
Martinez's hands now.
Well, tell that asshole
no barrel rolls.
Copy that, MAV.
CAPCOM.
Go.
Remote command.
Recovery.
Go.
Secondary recovery.
Pilot.
Go.
Copy. We're go.
Mission Control,
we are go for launch.
T-minus ten...
nine...
Main engine start.
eight...
seven...
Mooring clamps released.
About five seconds, Watney.
Hang on.
I'll see you in a few,
Commander.
four...
three...
two...
one.
Velocity,
741 meters per second.
Altitude, 1350 meters.
That's too low.
It's fighting me.
Watney, do you read?
Booster
separation complete.
Velocity, 850.
Altitude, 1843.
He's well below
target altitude.
How far below?
Checking.
Watney.
Do you read?
He's probably
passed out.
He pulled 12 g's
on the ascent.
Give him a few minutes.
Copy that.
Main shutdown
in three...
two, one...
shutdown.
Back to
automatic guidance.
Shutdown confirmed.
Fuel reserves depleted.
Watney?
Do you read?
It seems there's some
sort of problem
with the transmission.
I have interval pings.
Intercept velocity will be
11 meters per second.
I can make that work.
Distance
at intercept will be...
We'll be 68 kilometers apart.
68 kilometers?
Did she just say
Come on, guys,
keep it together.
Work the problem.
Johanssen, time to intercept?
39 minutes,
12 seconds.
Martinez, what if we
point our thrusters
in the same direction?
Well, it depends how much fuel
you wanna save...
for the altitude adjustments
for the trip home.
How much do you need?
I can get by with about 20%
of what we have left.
If we use 75.5% of remaining
altitude-adjust fuel...
that will bring the intercept
range to zero.
Do it.
Hang on. It brings
the range to zero...
but the intercept velocity
will be 42 meters per second.
And that's way too fast.
Then we'll have 39 minutes
to figure out
how to slow down.
Martinez, burn the jets.
Copy that.
MAV to Hermes.
Watney?
Affirmative.
What's your status?
My chest hurts.
I broke my ribs.
How are you?
We're working on
getting to you.
There was a complication
during launch.
Copy that.
How bad is it?
We've corrected
the intercept range,
but we've got a problem
with intercept velocity.
How big a problem?
42 meters a second.
Well...
shit.
Commander, I have an idea.
Go ahead, Mark.
Well, if I can find
something sharp in here...
and poke a hole in the glove
of my EVA suit...
I could use the escaping air
as a thruster...
and fly towards you.
It would be easy to control
because it would be on my arm.
I can't see you having
any control if you did that.
You'd be eyeballing
the intercept
using a thrust vector
you can barely control.
Yes, those are all
very good points.
But consider this.
I'd get to fly around
like Iron Man.
Commander...
let's go Iron Man.
This is unexpected IOS.
Communication lost. Stand by.
Maybe it's not the worst idea.
No, it is the worst idea.
It's the worst idea ever.
Not what he said.
Using atmosphere as thrust.
What happens
if we blow the VAL?
Wait, you want to open
the vehicular airlock?
It'll give us a good kick.
But also blow
the nose off the ship.
And all the air would leave
and we need air to not die.
We would seal the bridge
and the reactor room.
Everywhere else
would go vacuo.
Vogel.
Go ahead, Commander.
I need you to come inside
and make a... bomb.
Again, Commander?
You're a chemist.
Can you make a bomb with
what you have on board?
Probably.
But I feel obliged to mention
that setting off
an explosive device...
in a spacecraft
is a terrible, terrible idea.
Hang on. You guys making
a bomb without me?
Copy that.
Can you do it?
Ja.
Houston, be advised.
We are going to deliberately
breach the VAL
to produce a reverse thrust.
Beck, leave your suit on.
Meet Johanssen in Airlock 1.
We'll open the outer door.
I need you to place the charge
on the inner door.
Climb back to Airlock 2
along the hull.
Copy. I'm on my way.
I'm in, Commander.
Copy that.
Vogel, where are you?
I'm in the kitchen.
Okay.
Commander...
I can't let you
go through with this.
I am prepared to cut the suit.
Absolutely not.
See, the thing is,
I'm selfish.
I want all the memorials back
home to be about me.
Just me.
I should have left
this guy on Mars.
Hey.
Sugar?
Yeah.
Can you hold this?
Liquid oxygen...
and some stain remover
that contains ammonia.
This thing here
is five times stronger
than a stick of dynamite.
How do we activate it?
Can you connect this to
one of our lighting panels?
Careful.
Open Airlock 1.
I'm on
the way to Beck.
Let's just hope
this is a good idea, guys.
It is.
Open A 1.
Hi.
Hey.
You got it?
Mmm.
Make sure you're not in here
when this thing goes off.
Hey.
Be careful out there.
In space.
Don't tell anyone
I did that.
Bomb set.
Leaving Airlock 1.
Guys,
I'm running the numbers,
and even with
optimal VAL blow...
we're gonna be off
on our angle.
What's the intercept
distance? Johanssen?
260 meters, approximate.
That's too far.
Commander?
Martinez, close the door.
Open D3.
And leave it open.
Open B2.
Johanssen...
time to VAL blow
after initiate?
15 seconds.
We sure know
how to cut it close.
Commander?
Distance is too far.
I'm going out.
I can do this.
It's not a debate.
I'm not risking
another crew member.
Beck's returned.
Johanssen, initiate the bomb.
Ten seconds.
Strap in.
Five, four...
Three...
Brace for deceleration.
two...
one.
Activating Panel 41.
Bridge seal holding.
What's the damage?
Worry about that later.
What's the relative velocity?
12 meters per second.
Copy.
Hook me up.
Done.
I have visual on the MAV.
What's the intercept range?
I'm checking.
312 meters.
Did you say 312?
Great. I'll wave at you guys
as I go by.
Oh!
I can't get to you, Mark.
You're too far.
I'm not gonna make it.
I know.
Beck, unhook me.
I'm going after him.
Commander, I got this.
Mark, report.
On my way, Commander.
Damn it.
Johanssen, what's my relative
velocity to Mark?
5.2 meters per second.
Copy. Adjusting course.
3. 1 meters
per second.
Distance to target, 24 meters.
11 meters to target.
Six meters.
Hold on, Mark.
I got him.
Way to go, Iron Man.
Beck, pull us in.
It's good
to see you.
You...
have terrible taste in music.
Houston,
this is Hermes actual.
We got him.
Watney is secure.
Contact in outer
space with Mark Watney.
After a very long time,
they have done
what many people thought
was impossible.
Mission confirmation:
Mark Watney has been
successfully rescued.
Grab a hold of him.
Hey, handsome!
Beck, close the hatch.
Hey, guys!
Houston,
six crew safely aboard.
This is huge moment for
this nation, for the world...
and indeed, for
international space travel.
I can't believe
anything you do works.
Hey!
Oh, God.
I can't believe it.
There's a little smell
going on over there, bud.
I know. I haven't had a shower
in a year and a half.
Don't make me laugh,
I have broken ribs.
Hey, there.
Morning, sir.
It's an honor, sir.
Sir.
Morning, sir.
Welcome to the
Astronaut Candidate Program.
Now pay attention,
because this could
save your life.
Trust me, I know
what I'm talking about.
Let me get a few things out
of the way, right off the bat.
Yes, I did in fact survive
on a deserted planet
by farming in my own shit.
Yes, it's actually worse
than it sounds.
So let's not talk
about that ever again.
The other question I get
most frequently is...
"When I was up there,
stranded by myself...
"did I think
I was going to die?"
Yes, absolutely.
And that's what you need
to know going in
because it's going
to happen to you.
This is space.
It does not cooperate.
At some point, everything is
going to go south on you.
Everything is going
to go south
and you're going to say,
"This is it.
"This is how I end."
Now, you can either
accept that...
or you can get to work.
That's all it is.
You just begin.
You do the math.
You solve one problem...
then you solve the next one.
And then the next.
And if you solve
enough problems,
you get to come home.
All right, questions?
Once
Mission Control completes
their pre-flight checks...
we'll begin launch procedures.
The Ares 5 team will
rendezvous with the Hermes...
approximately 48 minutes
after launch.
From there,
they will have 414 days
of space travel ahead of them.
Have the goals changed
from the previous mission...
to the Ares 5 program?
And what do you hope to
achieve this time around?
Well, no. The goals
have always been the same
for the Ares program.
This time, of course,
we hope to bring
all the astronauts
back at the same time.
Flight,
Guidance check complete.
Copy, Guidance.
This is Flight.
We are go for launch,
on schedule.
Final aerosurface
checks are complete...
as everything remains a go
for the launch of the Ares 5.
20 seconds.
Proceeding with the count.
T-minus 10... 9...
Main engine start.
7... 6... 5... 4...
three... two... one.
And liftoff.
As the crew of the Ares 5...
begin the next chapter
of American space exploration.
Pressures look good.
Wow. Good shot.
There you have it.
Five years after the rescue
of astronaut Mark Watney...
an Ares 5 is on its way
to Mars.
First I was afraid
I was petrified
Kept thinking I could never
live without you by my side
But then I spent
so many nights
Thinking how
you did me wrong
And I grew strong
and I learned how to get along
And so you're back
from outer space
I just walked in
to find you here
With that sad look
upon your face
I should have changed
that stupid lock
I should have made you
leave your key
If I had known
for just one second
You'd be back to bother me
Boy,
now go, walk out the door
Just turn around now 'cause
you're not welcome anymore
Weren't you the one who
tried to hurt me with goodbye?
Did you think I'd crumble?
Did you think
I'd lay down and die?
Oh, no, not I
I will survive
For as long as
I know how to love
I know I'll stay alive
I've got all my life to live
And I've got
all my love to give
And I'll survive
I will survive
Hey, hey
Boy,
now go, walk out the door
Just turn around now 'cause
you're not welcome anymore
Weren't you the one who
tried to break me with goodbye?
Did you think I'd crumble?
Did you think
I'd lay down and die?
Oh, no, not I
I will survive
For as long as
I know how to love
I know I'll stay alive
I've got all my life to live
And I've got
all my love to give
And I'll survive
I will survive